Guide to the Imre Forbáth diaries,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Imre Forbáth Diaries,
1900-1943.
Forbáth, Imre.
2 linear ft. (4 document boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library. Bakhmeteff Archive New York, NY. 10027
BA#0527
7269482
This collection comprises twenty one journals of Imre Forbath (ака Emerich Forbath), one of the greatest engineers in Europe. These diaries span the period from 1900 to 1943.
History
Imre Forbáth (aka Emerich Forbath) was born in 1875 and died in 1944. One of the greatest engineers in Europe, he lived during the turbulent final decades of the Habsburg Monarchy, the First World War, the troubled Twenties and Thirties, and the Second World War. He was an eyewitness to many of the historic events of these times.
The young Hungarian-Jewish engineer Forbáth started his career as a civil engineer in Frankfurt and Berlin after attending universities in the Austro-Hungarian Empire and in Germany. He later worked in cities all over Europe in this period of rapid urban growth. He became known as one of the greatest engineers in Europe.
Imre Forbáth took part in the canalization of the major European rivers and in the designing of ports. He also worked on such urban infrastructure projects as water supply, sewage systems, gas works, and power plants. The nitrogen factory he directed for seventeen years, gaining for it an international reputation, still exists in Romania.
His peers regarded him as the best writer on city planning of his time. Forbáth published articles in professional journals and elsewhere on a weekly basis. In 1906, he became a private professor at the Budapest Technical University. Imre Forbáth was regarded as one of the leading figures in Budapest’s engineering and political worlds.
It was his fate to be present during many important historical events. Imre Forbáth took part in the First World War as an engineer with the Austro-Hungarian forces. His division was sent to Przemysl, which was besieged by the Russians. In his journal, he writes movingly about conditions in the surrounded fortress. When all their food ran out, the Austro-Hungarian troops had to surrender. This was one of the crucial moments of the war for Austria-Hungary. Forbáth’s account of this event is the only detailed one that has survived.
After the surrender of the fortress, he became a prisoner of war in Russia with his fellow soldiers and was taken to Siberia, to the cities of Tobolsk and Petropavlovsk, from which he managed to escape. He appeared in Moscow eight months after the Russian Revolution of 1917. He returned to Hungary when a Soviet republic was established there, too, during 1919.
His house and property were nationalized, but he was looked upon with respect by the revolutionaries as one of Budapest’s leading engineers. He held a position under the regime but resigned before it collapsed. The treaty of Trianon formally ended the First World War for Hungary in 1920, completely redrawing the country’s borders.
Forbáth kept his intellectual outlook and optimism for a better future alive throughout this disturbed period. His historical writings, unlike his technical ones, remained unknown and unpublished during his lifetime. Other than a few lines in biographical dictionary articles, nothing was written about his life in Hungary or elsewhere in Europe. Even the fact of his tragic death in the Holocaust in 1944 was not known. The Hungarian biographical lexicon and the Report of the Hungarian Hydraulic Society give his year of death as around 1952.
Scope and Content
The collection contains twenty one journals of Imre Forbath (aka Emerich Forbath), Hungarian engineer. The handwritten journals span the period from 1900 to 1943 and cover many important historical events and provide a valuable record on twentieth-century Hungarian and European history, history of technology, culture, and political life.
There is also two photographs, one letter, one business card, and one book-plate found as inserts in the diaries and placed in one folder.
The Budapest Archive has some documents from György Forbáth, engineer, who escaped from Russian captivity. Most likely, these are also a part of Imre Forbáth’s legacy.
Arrangement
Diaries arranged in chronological order. Various inserts found in journals are placed in one folder and stored at the end of the collection in Box 4.
Description of the each journal includes a summary of the content and alphabetical list of people, writings, public presentation, and works mentioned in the journal.
Subjects
Austria--History--1867-1918.; Europe--History--20th century.; Hungary--History--20th century.; City Planning.; Civil engineering--Hungary--20th century.; Civil engineering--Europe--20th century.; Hydraulic engineering--Europe--20th centruy.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945.; Diaries.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Pauline Forbáth and William E.Forbáth Gift 2000
Finding aid in repository and online
- Imre Forbáth Diaries, 1900-1943
  - Journal 1: March 29, 1900 - November 31, 1901 (Box 1)
    At the time of his first entries, Imre Forbáth is still using his original last name of Fischer. He is twenty-five years old, fluent in Hungarian, German, and French, a recent graduate of the Technical Universities of Vienna, Zurich, and Berlin. Imre Forbáth records his opinions on the latest developments in literature, philosophy, and music. While employed as a civil engineer for the city of Magdeburg, he works on his doctoral dissertation. The young civil engineer falls in love with Trüdchen, a German Christian woman, but has to break up with her. He writes a sensitive reflection on the relationship between Christians and Jews at this time. Conscripted into the Austro-Hungarian army, he is sent to Croatia for military training. While there he records the solar eclipse of May 15, 1901. He wins third place in an international competition for city planning in Bergen. Mother sells her house.
    Places mentioned:
    Bergen
    Budapest
    Cologne
    Érsekujvár
    Magdeburg
    People mentioned:
    Hilson
    Koppány, Géza
    Kramer
    Lüschen
    Trüdchen
    Unterführung Schörer
    Writings of this Period:
    Bau der Städte an Flüssen (Building of the Cities by the Rivers)
    Canalisation von Mailand (Canalization of Milan)
    Chicago Arkadische Canal (Arched Canal of Chicago)
    Kikötőkerdes: Frankfurt, Mainz, Düsseldorf, Ludvigshafen, Dreschen kikötőirol (Studies on the Frankfurt, Mainz, Düsseldorf, Ludwigshafen, and Dreschen Ports)
    Mannheim Csatornázási Terve (Canalization Plans for Mannheim)
    Muhlheim Csatornázási Tervei (Canalization Plans for Mühlheim)
    Nemet Mérnökok Helyzeterol (About the Lives of the German Engineers)
    Nordbrücke Electricitätswerk (Power Plant of Nordbrücke)
    Ontozes Városi Szennyvízekkel (Irrigating with Sewage from the City)
    Studien von der Riesenfelder (Studies on the Sewage Farms)
    Public Presentations made:
    A városok kozegeszsegugyerol a szennycsatornakat erintve (Cities’ Common Health Considering Sewers), Engineers’ Society (Mernok Egylet)
    A Vaskapu szabalyozásáról (Regulation of the Vaskapu), Engineers’ Society (Mernok Egylet)
    Works of this period:
    Canal of Dwigue
    Canal of Nyitra
    Canal of Sarajevo
  - Journal 2: December 1, 1901 - October 16, 1904 (Box 1)
    At this time, the writer of the journals uses the family name “Forbáth-Fischer.” He is a paid employee of the city of Frankfurt, working as a civil engineer. He is a member of the Society of Engineers of Frankfurt, as well as of the city’s Skittles Society. He is published regularly in the Technicians’ Association Journal. After getting his Austrian diploma recognized, he earns a doctorate with honors in Darmstadt (his thesis: Stadtebau in Alten und Neuer Zeit/ City Building in the Past and Present). He takes part in a trial concerning Magdeburg’s building supplies. In 1903, Imre Forbáth quits his job in Frankfurt and moves to Berlin, where he becomes head engineer and assistant principal of the office of civil engineering. Rapidly expanding opportunities in the field of city building bring him home to Hungary, where Imre Forbáth establishes a private engineering office in Pest. He loses the network of contacts in government and engineering circles that he had built up in Germany and has to develop a new one. Still quite a young man, he sets out to find work for his private engineering firm. Forbáth meets all the major political leaders of Hungarian cities where improvements are being undertaken. He holds liberal political views, which make him unique in his conservative circle. In Pest, he encounters ultra-radical socialist views for the first time in his life. The young engineer longs to live in England or America. He reads widely and keeps up with everything new in cultural life. Imre Forbáth publishes articles, mainly about the building of ports. For hygienic reasons, cities begin to build slaughterhouses. Forbáth’s plans win first place in a competition for a slaughterhouse in Altenesse. The family attends Joseph's wedding. Mother lives in Vienna. Uncle Rudolph dies.
    Berlin
    Darmstadt
    Frankfurt
    Alesius
    Altheim
    Alzheim
    Bella
    Berg and Peron
    Bohm
    Brix
    Cauter
    Drotleff
    Eichberg
    Faragó
    Farkass
    Feldman
    Finaly, István
    Földes (Professor)
    Ganzerzen, Kertz
    Goecke
    Hengsberger (his boss)
    Hiemesh (Mayor)
    Hoffman (builder)
    Hoffman (Professor at Darmstadt)
    Holeman, Philip
    Hoszpotzky
    Jossa
    Kassay
    Klonne
    Kolle (his boss)
    Kollischert (Dr.)
    Kovács, Aladár I.
    Lahmeyer, Salamon
    Láng, Károly
    Lastyánszky
    Lion
    Luthi
    Pfeffer
    Pichler
    Putzer
    Schongut
    Schutter (engineer)
    Tisza, István
    Tragen
    Uhlfelder
    Walbe (Professor at Darmstadt)
    Wecsei, Ferenc
    Zichmeister (Mayor of Győr)
    Writings of this period:
    A Mannheimi Kikötők (Ports of Mannheim)
    Altenessei Vágóhíd (Slaughterhouse of Altenesse)
    Bau der Städte an Flüssen: Frankfurt am Main (Building of Cities on Rivers: Frankfurt am Main)
    Belhajózási Kikötők Fontossága Forgalmi Szempontból (Importance of Ports for Inland Shipping Considering Traffic). Weekly Shipping Journal (Hajozasi Hetilap)
    Canalization of Sidney
    Cement Canal of Westend Centralblatt
    Egynehány Tengeri és Belhajózási Viteldíj Összehasonlítása (Comparison of Sea and Inland Shipping Fares).Weekly Informant (Heti Ertesito)
    Goethe. Zeitschrift für Binneuschrift 5
    Kanalisation der Altstadt von Magdeburg(Canalization of Magdeburg). Centralblatt Cistern of Dortmund; Centralblatt
    Kanalisation von Mailand (Canalization of Milan)
    Ports: Grieslan, Cologne, Dortmund, Kreflo
    Social und Wirtschlaftliche Vorarbeiten für Stadt Erneuerungsplane(Social and Scientific Preparations for Renovation Plans for Cities).Städtebau
    Városaink Rendezése (Arrangement of Our Cities). Szabolcs
    Városfejlesztési Munkák (City Development Works). Szabolcs
    Works on the Danube. Ges. Ing.
    A Majnafrankfurti Új Gabonasiló (Granary in Frankfurt am Main)
    A Vasút Új Javító Munkálatairól (About the New Train Repair Works), at Mérnök és Ép. Egylet (Engineer and Architect Society)
    Az Egészségügyi Mérnöki Munkák Hygiéniai és Közgazdasági Fontosságáról (Hygienic and Economical Importance of the Health Engineer Works)
    Az Új Vízvezetéki Díjszabályzat (New Water Supply Fees)
    Bau des Stadte an Flüssen in Alter und Neuer Zeit (City Building on Rivers in Old and New Times)
    Canalization in Nagyszeben (Nagyszebeni Csatornázás)
    Canalization in Rodelcheim (Rodelcheim-i Csatornázás)
    Frankfurt Mérnöki Hivataláról és Annak Munkáiról(Office of Engineering in Frankfurt and its Works)
    Nagyszebeni Villamosmű (Power Plant of Nagyszeben)
    Népszerű Főiskola-i Tanfolyam Vízvezeték és Csatorna Dolgában (Water Supply and Canalization Course at the Community College)
    Pozsonyi Vágóhíd (Slaughterhouse of Bratislava)
    Städtebaufragen(Questions of City Building)
    Szeged Közvágóhíd (Slaughterhouse of Szeged)
    Verkehrspolitische Wert der in Deutschland, Österreich and Ungarn Geplanten (Transportation Fares in Germany, Austria and Hungary)
    Wasserstrassen(Waterways), Mérnök és Épitesz Egylet (Engineer and Architect Society)
    Building of Mudling Hotel in Vienna
    Canal of Salzschlirf
    Canalization and Water Supply in Epstein
    Canalization and Water Supply of Kassa and Brasso
    Canalization of Eberwald
    Canalization of Königshütte
    City Building of Temesvár, Nyiregyháza, Szabadka, Gyongyos, and Miskolc
    City Building Plans for Nyiregyháza
    Plans and Building of Water Refinement Plant in Budapest
    Plans and Building of Water Refinement Plant in Nagyszeben
    Water Supply for Griesheim
    Water Supply in Nyitra
    Water Supply of Mainz, Epstein, Hofheim, Hatterheim, and Kriftel
    Water Supply of Pecs and Kecskemét
    Water Supply of Wilhelmhafen
  - Journal 3: October 26, 1904-April 19, 1908 (Box 1)
    The journal’s writer uses the name, “Forbát Imre Dr.” He opens a private engineering office in Budapest. He is not part of the Budapest elite yet, and still has to make a great effort to attract clients. He begins to learn English and travels to Manchester. He also travels to Berlin, Magdeburg, Frankfurt, and Constantinople. He earns his doctorate and becomes a lecturer at the Technical University in Budapest. Imre Forbáth takes his first steps in the field of communal politics. He is a member of the 48 Party, which supports the ideals of the 1848 Revolution, and takes part in national elections. He is a convinced liberal, excited about the political changes in France, especially the separation of church and state. He distances himself from Judaism, valuing it as a culture rather than a religion. He becomes one of Budapest’s leading figures in the fields of public works and city planning. He is a member of the Engineers’ Society. People want him to play a larger role in the city’s leadership, but he refuses. He is asked to appraise gas prices for Budapest. Banki paints his portrait. He wins second place at an international competition in Varna. He comes in first in the Ruscsuk canalization and water supply competition. He writes about the August 29, 1905 solar eclipse.
    Places Mentioned:
    Constantinople
    Manchester
    Varna
    Andrassy
    Apponyi, Count
    Barabas, Bela
    Bartok, Bela
    Becker
    Cigler (professor)
    Circle, Erzsébet
    Circle, Lipot
    Devecis
    Fedak, Sari
    Hatvany, Jozsef
    Heltai, Jeno
    Hollo, Lajos
    Kajlinger
    Kovacs (professor)
    Leon
    Manger, Armin
    Markus, Jozsef
    Szalay, Lajos (Mayor)
    Szekely, Bertalan
    Szilagyi, Dezso
    Tatrai, Lajos (student)
    Tolnai, Lajos
    A lakaskerdes és Budapest jovoje (Question of Housing and the Future of Budapest); Budapest, 1906
    A vízmuvek rentabilitásáról (About the Profit of the Water Supplies)
    Amerikanische Abwasser Reimsgsanhenge (American Water Connections)
    Bebauung der Aussengesartiere Budapests (Building of Budapest’s Suburbs)
    Berechnung von Städten (Calculation of the Cities)
    Budapest jovoje (Future of Budapest)
    Haupstädtische Bau(Building of the Capital)
    Kanalisation der Stadt Nagyszeben (Canalization of Nagyszeben)
    Kleinwohnungsfürsorge in Glasgow (Low-Income Housing in Glasgow), Gesundheit
    Kleinwohnungsfürsorge in Sheffield (Low-Income Housing in Sheffield), Gesundheit
    Kleinwohnunksfürsorge in Englischen Städten (Low-Income Housing in the Cities of England), Leipzig, 1906
    Lage der Ingenieure in Ungarn (Position of the Engineer in Hungary)
    Muszaki teendoink városaink fejlesztese korul (Technical Works about the Development of Our Cities); Vallalkozok Közlönye
    Ontozes Városi szennyvízekkel (Watering with City Sewage); Budapest, 1905
    Parlament und Freiheitsplatz Viertel in Budapest (Parliament and the Freedom Square Buildings in Budapest)
    Ruscsuk víz és csatornázási tervei (Plans of the Water Supply and Canals of Ruscsuk)
    Városaink Muszaki Ugyei (Our Cities’ Engineering Problems)
    Public presentations made:
    A Kozigazgatasi birosag reformjai (Judicial Reforms of the Administration), Országos Igazsagugyi Muszaki Tanacs (National Technical Rights Committee)
    A Muszaki Kamara és a Koztisztsegviselok (Technical Chamber and the Administration)
    A városok csatornázásarol (On the Canalization of the Cities), Budapesti Muegyetem (Technical University of Budapest)
    Artezi furdok beepitendo hullammedence dolgaban (About Wave-Pools in Thermal Baths), Városháza (City Hall)
    Csatornázásrol és szennyvíz tisztitasrol (Canalization and Sewage Cleaning); Az Osztrak-Magyar Gaz-és Víztechnikusok Kongresszusa (Congress of Gas and Hydraulic Technicians of Austria-Hungary)
    Kozepes nagysagu városok rendzeserol (Planning Middle-Sized Cities), Budapesti Muegyetem (Technical University of Budapest)
    Ujabb torekvesek a városepites teren, celzassal a Budapesti szabalyozasra(New Plans in City Building: Regulation of Budapest); Mérnök Egylet (Engineer’s Society)
    Vagohid és Városterv (Slaughterhouse and City Planning), Varoshaza (City Hall)
    Városrendezes kozegeszsegugyi szempontbol szempontbol (City Organizing, Focusing on Civil Health Issues)
    Appraisal of the Stone Mine of Sator
    Canal of Varna
    Canalization of Nagydisznod and the Starch Factory of Csikosgornok
    Dam of Jozsefváros
    Drilling on the Danube for the Water Supply of Goldberg Factory
    Incinerator at Miskolc
    Incinerator in Bucharest
    Plant -Oil Factory of Pest
    Sewage for Hatvany Sugar Factory
    Sewage of Jaszbereny and Hatvan
    Spring of Csillaghegy
    Water Refinement Plant of Nagyszeben
    Water Sink of Vienna
    Water Supply of Zombori
    Water Supply, Sewer System, and Slaughterhouse of Vojvodina (Ujvidek)
    Water Works of Bratislava
    Water Works of Brussa, Nagyberek, Pancsova, Zagrab
    Water Works of Marko Street; Pest
    Watering of Vojvodina and Ruscsuk (Resicabánya)
    Works in Nagyenyed, Segesvár, and Brasso
    Works in Székesfehérvár, Tatabánya, Siofok, Szatmar, Felegyháza, Hodmezovásárhely, and Hatvan
    Works on the Slaughterhouse of Altesse
  - Journal 4: April 22, 1908-July 25, 1911 (Box 1)
    The author of the journals uses the name, “Imre Forbáth Dr.” He is a lecturer at the new Technical University and is elected to its governing body. He takes part in parliamentary election campaigns. People in many constituencies ask him to run for office, but he refuses. He wants to be financially secure first. He travels to France, Italy, Bulgaria, and Germany. He is the Hungarian representative at the International Exhibition on City Planning held in Berlin. He is one of the Hungarian delegates sent to the jubilee celebration in Rome. He travels to the World’s Fair in Brussels and visits Antwerp to take part in a city planning competition. Forbáth and Vargha submit plans for Antwerp, which take third place. Imre Forbáth’s lifestyle has changed; he is now part of the Hungarian elite, moving in circles beyond those of his family and profession.
    Brussels
    Bulgaria
    France
    Germany
    Rome
    Aigner, Rudolf
    Arnstein, Henrik
    Barczy (Mayor)
    Bartha, Kalman
    Batthyany, Tivadar
    Beck, Gyula
    Berbnady, György
    Bitto
    Bohm, Imre
    Brauserwetter
    Buzath
    Cazar
    Czipfer
    Darvai
    Domique
    Fenyvessy, Jozsef
    Ferenczi, Imre
    Furst, Laszlo
    Grunwald, Mor
    Grunwald, Vilmos
    Gyarmaty, Viktor
    Harrer
    Hederváry, Lehel
    Hegedus, Lorant
    Heltay, Ferenc
    Huszar (private professor)
    Koppany, Geza
    Kun, Gyula
    Lechner
    Lueger
    Mandells
    Merse, Pal
    Michailich
    Monillard
    Nemes, Marcell
    Nyary
    Parloff (Mayor)
    Reich
    Ripke, Ferenc
    Rock, István
    Romsanek (private professors)
    Rozsa, Ferenc
    Sandor, Pal
    Szabo, Jozsef
    Szilagyi, Ferenc
    Tory
    Ugron, Gabor
    Unger, Jozsef
    Vazsonyi, Vilmos
    Weiss, Albert
    Weiss, Manfred
    Werner, Hegeman (Dr.)
    Zala, György
    Zemplen
    A berlini Városepitesi kiallitasrol (On the City Building Exhibition in Berlin), Városok Lapja and Magyarország
    A Brassoi gat (Dam of Brasso), Ges. Ing.
    A fovaros muszaki adminisztraciojanak ujjaszervezeserol (On the Reorganization of the Technical Administration of the Capital), Lloyd
    A kissarmasi foldgaz Budapesten (Natural Gas of Kissarmás in Budapest), Fuggetlen Budapest
    A liberalis angol koltsegvetesol (Budget of Liberal England), Magyarország
    A Magyar-Dalmat vasutak vízellátásáról (Watering of the Magyar-Dalmat Railroads), Lloyd
    A soroksari Dunaag kikötőve valo kiepiteserol(Building a Port at Soroksár, Tributary of the Danube), published in every daily news
    Ankauf der Stadtbahnen / A fovárosi vasut megvetelerol (Purchase of the City’s Trolleys), Lloyd
    Antwerpen (In Antwerp), Strassebau, Halle
    Barczay nagy 95 milliardos epitesi programjarol (95-Billion Korona Building Program of Mayor Barczay), Lloyd
    Budapest forgalmarol (On Budapest’s Traffic), Lloyd
    Eisfrage (Question of Ice), Lloyd
    Gasfrage in Budapest / A Budapesti Gaz (Gas of Budapest), Lloyd
    Gedanken über die Brusseler Weltaustellung (Thoughts about the World’s Fair in Brussels), Lloyd
    Magyarország gazdasagi fejlodese (Hungary’s Economic Growth), Lloyd
    Mérnök és jogasz (Engineer and Lawyer), Városok Lapja
    Székesfehérvar, Lloyd
    Resicabánya vízellatasa (Watering of Resicabánya), Értesítő
    A foldalatti Budapestrol (On the Budapest Underground)
    A fovárosi Kozuzemek bevaltasanak folytatásáról (On the Community Factories of the Capital)
    A fovárosi villamostelepek bevaltásáról (On the Power Plant of the Capital), at Demokrata Kor (Democratic Circle)
    A gazkerdesrol. Grof Festetich Geza a francia-osztrak ajanlat ossszehasonlitasa (On the Problem of Gas)
    A lakaskerdes reformja (Housing Reform), at Magyar Tarsadalomtudomanyi Egylet (Hungarian Social Sciences Committee)
    A mérnöki hivatal reformjarol(On the Reform of the Engineering Administration)
    A Nagyszebeni csatornázásrol (Canalization in Nagyseben), Mérnökegylet
    A szekesfováros kozigazgatásáról hozott uj szabalyrendletek (New Regulations in the Capital), Közlöny
    Antwerpen (On Antwerp), at Mérnök Egylet (Engineer’s Committee)
    Az Erzsébet Sugarut terveinek elokeszitese (Erzsébet Boulevard, With Dezso Jasz), at Kozmunkatanacs (Committee of Community Works)
    Batthyányi teri hid tervpalyazat (Plan of the Batthyányi Square Bridge), at Mérnök Egylet (Engineer’s Committee)
    Goethes Stellung zu Gottheit und religion (Goethe’s Opinion on God and Religion), Lloyd
    Kertvárosok (Suburbs), Bratislava
    Modern városrendzes a nyugati országokban (Modern City Planning in the Western Countries, technical lectures)
    Ruhen von Boston / Bosztoni Városi Parkok (City Parks of Boston), Lloyd
    Sugarut (Parkway, with Dezso Jasz), at Kozmunkatanacs Committee of Community Works
    Városrendezesrol (City Building), at Muszaki egy eloadasok (Technical University lectures)
    Vízjogi targyalas Tencsenyben (Trial on Water Rights in Tencsény)
    Vízvezeték és csatornzas (Water Supply and Sewers), at Székesfehérvári Egylet (Committee of Székesfehérvár)
    Canalization of Deva
    Expert for Larduzzi in Miskolc
    Expert in Debrecen
    Infrastructure of Marosvásárhely, Nagybecskerek (Nagybuskerse), Beszterce, Resicza, Szatmar-nemeti, Nagyszeben, Brasso, Tatabánya, Viova River
    Infrastructure of Papa, Doman, Rimaszombat, Sziliacsfurdo
    Plans of Anina and Doman, Szabadka, Székesfehérvár, Lake Sosto
    Plans of Low-Income Housing in Kispest (For Sandor Wekerle)